<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise against images and pictures in churches. And an answer to those who object that the times are changed. Written by George Salteren, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Salteren, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93560</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E163_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872649</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93560)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 29:E163[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise against images and pictures in churches. And an answer to those who object that the times are changed. Written by George Salteren, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Salteren, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Lee, and are to be sold at the signe of the Turks head in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE againſt IMAGES. and PICTURES in Churches. And an Anſwer to thoſe who object that the times are changed.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>George Salteren,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Turks head in Fleet-ſtreet, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156945:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156945:2"/>
            <head>A TREATISE againſt IMAGES and PICTURS in Churches.</head>
            <head type="sub">And an Anſwer to thoſe who object that the Times are changed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He old Serpent, the father of lies, is ſtill the ſame; he is full of inventions and deviſes to draw men from god, and to bring them to deſtruction. And the wicked heart of man is ſtill like it ſelfe, apt to apprehend whatſoever that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſuggeſteth, ſo it be pleaſing to their depraved diſpoſitions, and corrupt affections.</p>
            <p>Although it bee moſt cleare and evident, that the ſetting up of the pictures of Saints in Churches, is, 1. no way warranted by the word of God. 2. but ſeverely prohibited, and condemned. 3. And therefore juſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed by our common prayers. 4. And ſo declared by the doctrine of our Church in the Homilies: yet he hath found a ſhift to ſay, that the Homilies were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156945:3"/>made for thoſe times, namely for the beginning of the Reformation, and therefore the more ſevere; but now the times are changed, and a milder courſe is taken. As if the whole Authority condemning theſe vanities, and abominations, depended only upon the Homilies, and not upon the eternall and immurable truth of Gods holy Word and Commandement. Let us not deceive our ſelves; for the neglect of Gods Commandements, which the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> calleth Rebellion, is as the ſinne of witchcraft, apt to delude and blinde us. But they that look into the cleare light of Gods word doe know that the negative precepts of Gods Law, <hi>Obligant ſemper, &amp; ad ſemper:</hi> as our Church, and all our godly, and reverend Biſhops, and learned Divines in their books, allowed, authoriſed, and publiſhed, have taught us. Theſe books alſo agree with the doctrine of the Homilies, that the words of Gods Law are to be taken by a <hi>Senechdoche ſpeciei, pro genere,</hi> according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. And the rules thereupon collected by the learned fathers of the Primitive Church, <hi>Auguſtine, Iſidor, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore the word graven Images muſt be extended to all Images, whether molten, carved, or painted; the word ſimilitude to all kindes of ſimilitude, though but in conceit; and the word <hi>(thou ſhalt not worſhip, nor bow downe to them)</hi> to all kindes of worſhip, though it bee but ſetting them <hi>in honorabili loco,</hi> as our Homilies ſpeake out of Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And this hath been taught us for truth now almoſt theſe 80 yeares together.</p>
            <p>And this truth is not made more ſtrong, but more cleare and evident to us, by the conſtant expoſitions of godly men both before and ſince the making of the Homilies. <hi>Vox populi Dei, vox Dei eſt, &amp; praxis Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156945:3"/>interpres praeceptorum:</hi> which yet is more manifeſt by the Lawes, Ordinances, Canons, and Conſtitutions, both Eccleſiaſticall, and Politick, as well conſequent, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current; and by the continuance and renewed confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Articles, and book of Common prayers, without alteration or qualification in this point: and laſtly, by the abſurdities of the Conſequents, that muſt bee inferred upon this new conceit of the change of times. For what will or can they ſay? If wee demand when this change was made, by whom, and by what authority, wherein, how declared, and how accepted? was the doctrine of the Homilies true then, and is it not ſo now? or was the ſenſe and meaning of the Law of God ſo then, and it is not ſo now? Is the truth of the eternall God mutable and temporary? Are Gods Lawes ſubject to times? Or is it not a meere non-ſenſe, or contradiction to ſay that Gods Law was once ſo to be underſtood; but not ſo now? Why then is the fact and judgement of that learned and godly Biſhop <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> together with the conſent of S. <hi>Hierom.</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the Elibertin Councell, and all the Primitive Church, the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the excellent godly Biſhops, <hi>Serenius, Naſsitienſis, Claudius, Thaurinenſis, Guilielmus Miniatenſis;</hi> whereof ſome with their hands, and all with their writings and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, did teare and break downe Pictures, and Images of Saints? Why are they ſo highly commended, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therein, by our late godly and learned Biſhops, and Doctors, <hi>Iewell</hi> of <hi>Sarum, Hall</hi> of <hi>Exon.</hi> uſher of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, Peter Martyr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Doctor <hi>Iames,</hi> Doctor <hi>Mayor</hi> the Catechiſt, and others; ſome of which books were new printed and ſet forth within theſe five yeares laſt paſt, together with that excellent book of Martyrs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156945:4"/>ordeined to be ſet open for every man to read in all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Churches, and Biſhops houſes. I demand therefore, when this change was made that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? was it within theſe three yeares, or two, or one? I demand alſo by whom, or by whoſe authority? For it is manifeſt, and knowne to all the world, that the moſt bleſſed Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> made none, but conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept her ſelfe to her word; <hi>ſemper eadem.</hi> Our moſt noble and learned king <hi>Iames</hi> made none; but by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation prefixed before the Common prayerbooke, and every yeare new printed, moſt ſtraitly prohibited all Innovations. Neither hath our moſt gratious, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King <hi>Charles</hi> made any; but by his Declaration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Articles moſt ſeverely forbiddeth all altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and that alſo within theſe five yeares. Who then are theſe that will have an Alteration or Innovation? And by whoſe authority, or by what meanes have they changed the times? Thirdly, how hath this change been made, inſtituted, or accepted? For, <hi>Leges inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur, cum promulgantur; confirmantur, cum moribus utentium approbantur:</hi> Lawes are then inſtituted when they are proclaimed; and are confirmed, when they are obſerved in the lives of the ſubjects. What hath been done in this kinde? Doe they think that Gods Lawes can bee altered by humane inventions? or that Lawes once, by ſupreme authority and publick conſent, made and approved, can without equall authority and conſent be altered and changed, by the conceits of private men? If they may by this trick ſhift off the doctrine of one Homily, why not of all the reſt? why not of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of reading the word of God, of Faith, of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of Chriſtian love and Charity, of good works, of Prayers, of repairing Churches, and laſtly alſo thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156945:4"/>moſt godly Homilies of obedience, and againſt diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and Rebellion, and ſo ſet every mans conſcience at liberty? Yea, why may they not proceed from the Homilies, and by the ſame reaſon reverſe alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrations of our Biſhops, and ordinations of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and all the Articles, Canons, and Conſtitutions, Lawes, and Statutes, aſwell of the Church, as of the State; and ſo bring all to confuſion? For if one Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that hath been now theſe 80. yeares almoſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and by ſo many Canons and conſtitutions may now ſo eaſily be rejected and annulled; why not all the reſt? If one Article may be ſo vacated, why not all? And if this ſetting up of Pictures grow once to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly allowed, and that theſe Imaginers or Imagers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Majeſties approbation (which God forbid) what ſhall we doe next? ſhall we ſtill goe to Church every Aſhwedneſday to curſe all ſetters up of Idols, and worſhippers of Images, and ſo to curſe every of us, both our ſelves, and one another? to curſe all our moſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and godly Biſhops; yea to curſe him and his, whom I for my part dare not name or think of, without a moſt ardent prayer to Almighty God for their both tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall bleſſedneſſe? I ſay not only every Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wedneſday, but every day, when we offer up to God our prayers, according to the godly order of our Common prayer book: Since that in uſing part we agree to the whole, and alſo to the intent and meaning of thoſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes allowed by our Church, and by all our godly and reverend Biſhops, from the firſt yeare of that excellent Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> to this inſtant time of the reigne of our moſt gracious King <hi>Charles.</hi> What fearfull things be theſe to think of? and yet how can they be avoyded, if once this gap be opened, that with a publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156945:5"/>of our publick ordinances theſe Pictures in Churches ſhall be publickly accepted?</p>
            <p>But becauſe ſome doe lightly eſteeme the authority of our Homilies, though made by moſt learned, godly, and reverend men; whereof ſome were Biſhops in the time of King <hi>Edward;</hi> and Marryrs und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Queene <hi>Mary</hi> unto death; others were Martyrs by baniſhment under Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Biſhops in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> time; which Homilies do utterly condemn the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of all Images, called the Images or Pictures of Saints in Churches: I have thought good to ſet down certaine ſentences of the holy Scriptures, together with the expoſitions, as well of the Ancient Doctors, and Fathers, as of our moſt learned and reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (whereof ſome are yet living) and alſo of Catechiſmes that by comparing the one with the other, it may plainly appeare by their unanimous conſent, that the ſetting up of ſuch Images and Pictures in Churches, is and hath been moſt juſtly declared, to bee unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and accurſed, not for any temporall, but for eternall reaſons; <hi>viz.</hi> as being directly againſt the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, <hi>ſc.</hi> The ſecond Comamandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any Image, nor the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of any thing, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not bow down, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here upon ſayth <hi>Tertullian <note place="margin">Tertul. de Idol.</note> principale crimen generis humani ſummus ſaeculireatus, tota cauſa judicii, Idololatria.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>graecè ſormam ſonat, ab eo per diminutionem I dolum deductum, aequè apud nos formulam fecit. Inde omnis forma vel formula Idolum ſe dici expoſcit; Inde Idololatria omnis circa omne Idolum famulatus &amp; ſervitus: Inde omnes Idoli Artifex ejuſdem &amp; unius eſt criminis. Idolum tàm fleri, quàm coli Deus prohibet. Quantò praecedit ut fiat
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156945:5"/>quod coli poſsit, tantò prius eſt ne fiat, ſi coli non licet. Prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hanc cauſam ad eradicandum ſcil. materiam Idololatriae, Lex divina proclamat; Ne feceritis Idolum, &amp; conjungens, neque ſimilitudinem eorum quae in Coelo ſunt, &amp; quae in terra, &amp; quae in mari. Omnia colit humanus error, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ipſum omnium Conditorem: eorum imagines, idola, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum conſecratio, idololatria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ait quidam, cur ergo</hi> Moſes <hi>in eremo ſimulacrum ſerpentis ex aere fecit? Benè, quod idem Deus &amp; Lege vetuit ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem ſieri, &amp; extraordinario praecepto ſerpentis ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem interdixit, ſi eundem Deum obſervas, habes legem ejus, ne feceris ſimilitudinem: Si &amp; praeceptum factae poſtea ſimilitudinis reſpicis, &amp; tu imitare Moſen; ne facias ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus legem ſimulacrum aliquod, niſi &amp; tibi Deus juſſerit. Facio, ait quidam, non colo: imo tu colis qui facis ut coli poſsint; colis autem non ſpiritu viliſsimi nidoris alicujus, ſed tuo proprio, nec animâ pecudis impenſâ, ſed animâ tuâ. Illis ingenium tuum immolas, illis ſudorem libas, illis pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatiam accendis:</hi> might he not have ſaid alſo, <hi>illis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniam erogas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Idolatry is the principall crime of mankinde, the greateſt guilt of the world, the totall cauſe of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Greek ſignifies a forme; from thence by diminution is an Idol derived, which in like manner ſignifies a <hi>formula,</hi> or little forme; from whence every forme, be it little or great, may be rightly termed an Idol: ſo that Idolatry is all kinde of ſervice or worſhip of any Idol whatſoever: and from thence every maker of an Idol is guilty of one and the ſelfe ſame crime. God prohibiteth that an Idol ſhould be as well made, as bowed downe unto. As much as it is avaylable that that ſhould be made, which may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, by ſo much it is better that that ſhould not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156945:6"/>be made which may not be adored: For this cauſe <hi>i. e.</hi> the extirpating of occaſion of Idolatry; the divine law proclaimeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image,</hi> adding, <hi>nor the likeneſſe of any thing in heaven, nor in the earth, nor in the ſea:</hi> For humane vanity is apt to worſhip any thing, excepting only the Creator of all things; the Images and Idols of which, and the conſecration of them is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>But ſome one will ſay, why then did <hi>Moſes</hi> make the image of a ſerpent in braſſe? Well, becauſe the ſame God hath forbidden by his law, that a likeneſſe ſhould be made, and by an extraordinary precept hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the likeneſſe of a ſerpent. If thou honour the ſame God, thou haſt his law; <hi>Thou ſhalt not make any likeneſſe:</hi> and if thou reſpect the precept, the Image which was made after, doe thou in like manner imitate <hi>Moſes:</hi> make not to thy ſelfe any Image againſt the law, unleſſe thou art commanded by God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was. I make them, ſayes one, but I worſhip them not: yes, thou doſt worſhip them who makeſt them; for now they may be worſhipped: yea thou worſhippeſt them not with the ſpirit of any vile creature, but thine owne; nor to the hazard of the ſoule of a beaſt, but thine owne ſoule. To them thou doſt offer up thy wit, thy labour, and thine art, and might he not have ſaid, to them thou giveſt chy money?</p>
            <p>And having examined, and condemned A ſtrology, Magick, and other idolatrous Arts, he addeth in the end this generall concluſion: <hi>Nulla igitur ars, nulla pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsio, nulla negotiatio, quae quid, aut in ſtruendis, aut in formandis idolis, adminiſtrat, carere poterit titulo idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae.</hi> Therefore no art, no trade, nor profeſſion which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth any thing to the making or forming of Idols
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156945:6"/>can be freed from the name of Idolatry. Yet he goeth forward, and ſheweth how Idolatry may be committed in other actions of our life, by ſeeing, hearing, &amp;c. He addeth, <hi>Omnis patientia ejuſmodi Idololatria:</hi> That all permiſſion of the ſame is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>So this ancient and learned Doctor of the Church hath expounded to us the ſecond Commandement: firſt, ſhewing the true meaning and large extent of the word <hi>Idolum,</hi> that it comprehendeth as much as the word <hi>forma,</hi> which all learned Logicians doe know is the fourth <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the predicament of quality; and ſo comprehendeth all things which may be reduced to that <hi>ſpecies,</hi> either by Aequipollence, or Subdiviſion, whether it be Image, or <hi>ſimulacrum,</hi> or <hi>effigies</hi> (as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> himſelfe ſpeaketh upon 1 <hi>Io.</hi> 5.) or whether it be exemplar, or <hi>ſpecies,</hi> as the learned Biſhop <hi>Caſtaneas</hi> ſheweth, or Statue, or Picture, as Divines do teach.</p>
            <p>And yet he addeth <hi>ſimilitudinem</hi> or likeneſſe, a word much more large, as that which runneth throughout all the foure <hi>ſpecies</hi> of quality, and extendeth as well to the inviſible conceits and imaginations of our minde, as to the exterior viſible formes and figures; for what is there, either in the world, or out of the world, in act or in conceit, but it may be called <hi>ſimile,</hi> or <hi>diſsimile,</hi> like, or unlike? And againe, <hi>eorum quae in Coelo, quae in terra, quae in mari &amp;c. Omnia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>colit humanus error praeter ipſum omnium Conditorem.</hi> And <hi>qui dixit omnia, nihil omiſit, Heb.</hi> 2.8. of thoſe things which are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in the earth, in the ſea, &amp;c. humane errour wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth any, excepting only the Creatour of all. And hee who hath ſpoken all, hath omitted nothing, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he anſwereth the objection of the brazen
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156945:7"/>ſerpent made by <hi>Moſes;</hi> to which alſo may be reduced (ſaith our excellent learned Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> with the conſent of all our Church) the making of the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> and as I conceive the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Picture upon his Coyne, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>To all which, that anſwer which this moſt learned Doctor maketh, will ſerve: Well and good (ſayth hee, according to the Tranſlation of our <hi>Iewell.</hi>) One and the ſame God, both by his generall Law forbade any Image to be made; and alſo by his extraordinary and ſpeciall commandement willed an Image of a ſerpent to be made. If thou be obedient to the ſame God, thou haſt his law; make thou no Image: But if thou have regard to the Image of the ſerpent that was made after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by <hi>Moſes,</hi> then doe thou as <hi>Moſes</hi> did; make not any Image againſt the law, unleſſe God command thee, as hee did <hi>Moſes;</hi> for God is free and ſubject to no law; Hee commandeth us and not himſelfe, ſaith our <hi>Iewell.</hi> And for the Picture of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> may not I adde, make no Image unleſſe our Saviour Chriſt allow it, as he did <hi>Caeſars</hi> Picture. Or which at leſtwiſe the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Primitive Church, within the firſt foure hundred yeers after our Saviours birth, hath declared to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the ſign of the Croſſe, May not I ſay alſo upon the ſame grounds, Make thou no Image of thoſe things, whoſe forme &amp; countenance, God &amp; our Saviour Chriſt would have to be altogether hidden, unknown, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; as <hi>Moſes</hi> body, the countenance of Chriſt, of his Apoſtles, of the Prophets, of the Martyrs &amp; Saints; Of whom no true Image can be made, becauſe it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known of what forme or countenance any of them were? And therefore as ſoon as any Image is made of them, ſtraightway a lie is made, ſayth our Church in her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:156945:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſaid learned Doctor <hi>Tertullian</hi> goeth forward to anſwer another objection, <hi>Facio (ait quidam) non colo,</hi> as now ſome do ſay; we ſet them up for orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not to worſhip; to which he anſwereth in like ſort, as our Church doth in her Homilies; Yes, thou worſhippeſt them, which makeſt them, becauſe now they may been worſhipped; yea, thou worſhippeſt them thy ſelfe, to them thou offereſt up thy ſpirit and thy ſoule; namely, thy wit, thy labour, thy skill and cunning; And might he not have ſaid, thy money, and thy time, which is thy life? thus he ſheweth how large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word <hi>Colere</hi> is to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, he anſwereth divers other objections and doubts, ſhewing with all how many wayes Idolatry may be committed; yea, ſometimes by giving an almes to a poore body, accepting his thanks or prayers in ſome ſort; adding that generall ſentence, that patience is ſometimes Idolatry, &amp;c. So largely doth this godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expound this Commandement: To whoſe judgment, all the holy Fathers of the Primitive Church, within foure hundred yeeres after the birth of our Saviour, which is the proper time of the true Fathers, as by <hi>Vincentius</hi> may bee collected, and all our godly and reverend Biſhops, for almoſt 80. yeeres now together, as well in their Authenticall Articles, Canons, and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in their Dogmaticall Books, Sermons, and Catechiſmes allowed, as in their Polemicall diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have agreed and confirmed: Which I note part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtop the mouthes of ſome that would make this a Schoole point, or Controverſie; partly to touch the timidity and coldneſſe, ſhall I ſay, or unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of others, which are afraid to ſpeak of that in the Pulpit, which is allowed and commanded to bee read publickly and taught in our common Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156945:8"/>as well by every good <hi>Pater-familias,</hi> as by every Preacher, as by that which followeth ſhall appear; for indeed, the whole Scripture, even all the old &amp; new Teſtament are but a very ſhort and briefe Epitome, of the infinite wiſdome, truth, mercy, and juſtice, of our heavenly Father; and of his incomprehenſible love to us in our Lord Chriſt Jeſus, paſſing all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and therefore in moſt places, and ſpecially in the Decalogue, is to bee taken Synechdochically, of the part for the whole, <hi>ſpeciei pro genere, continentis pro contento, &amp;c.</hi> in the largeſt ſenſe that the rule of faith will admit, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and all other learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have taught us. Let us go forward therefore.</p>
            <p>Our ſaid learned and reverend Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to <hi>Harding;</hi> pag. 498. citeth ſome of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of <hi>Tertullian</hi> above mentioned, approving the ſame; which book of <hi>Iewell's,</hi> is by order of our godly Biſhops ſet up in all our Cathedrall Churches, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to be read of all men that will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Deus in ſumma regione quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendus eſt; Quare dubium non eſt, quin religio nulla ſit ubicunque eſt Simulacram. Nam ſi Religio ex Divinis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſt, Divini autem nihil eſt, niſi ex Coeleſtibus rebus, carent ergo Religione Simulacra.</hi> Which by all our Biſhops and whole Church, in the Homilies, is thus rendred: <hi>God is to bee ſought in the higheſt Region; Wherefore there is no doubt, but that no Religion is in that place, whereſoever any Image is:</hi> For if Religion ſtand in godly things, and there is no godlineſſe, but in heavenly things; then are Images without Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Note that he ſayth there is no Religion, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there is <hi>Simulacrum, any Image;</hi> ſo that the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Image to be in a place, excludeth Religion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156945:8"/>out of that place; <hi>Patientia eſt Idololatria,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tertull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine of our Homilies is confirmed by the Canons made 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Iacobi Regis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever affirmeth that the 35<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of the Doctrine of the Church of England is erroneous (which Article teacheth us, that the Homilies againſt the perill of Idolatry, containe good and wholeſome Doctrine, and very neceſſary for theſe times) he that affirmeth the ſayd Article to bee enoneous, is excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> by the fifth Canon; but he that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up Images of Saints in Churches, or affirmeth that it is lawfull, to ſet up Images of Saints in Churches, in ſo contradicting the Homilies by word or deed, affirmeth that the ſaid Article is errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for <hi>negatio ſive in verbis, ſive in factis;</hi> a negation either in word or deed, &amp;c. is all one, ſay both Divines and Lawyers, according to Saint <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Tertul. de Idol. Nazianzen in Tetraſt.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin, Quid verba audiam c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m facta videam? Weſemberch. Res ipſa loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</hi> Why ſhall I hearken to words when I ſee deeds? the thing it ſelfe doth make it evident, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore, hee that ſetteth up Images of Saints in Churches, or affirmeth that it is lawful to ſet them up in Churches, is excommunicate <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> by the Canon. See his Majeſties Declaration, that the Articles do containe the true Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And let every man be well adviſed, whether hee will oppugne his Majeſties Declaration or not: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſetter up of ſuch Images in Churches, only excommunicate, by the Canon; but accurſed alſo by our Church in the Common-Prayer-Book, upon the place of <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. next following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curſed is the man that maketh any graven or molten
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156945:9"/>Image, an abomination unto the Lord, the work of the hands of the crafts-man, and putteth it in a ſecret place, Deut.</hi> 27.25.</p>
            <p>This Curſe is yeerly read in our Churches, by the Canon of our Common-Prayer-Book, upon the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> and the ſame is yeerly repeated with moſt ſolemne, and devout Imprecation or commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon every Aſhwenſday: And what the ſence and meaning of the ſaid Curſe importeth, is declared like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by our Church, in the Homilies appointed to be read in our Churches by the Common-Prayer-Book, Articles, and Injunctions, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>Againſt Idolatry, pag.</hi> 63. <hi>Curſed bee the man, &amp;c.</hi> Thus ſayth God. For at that time, no man durſt have or worſhip Images openly, but in corners onely. And the whole world being the great Temple of God, he that in any corner thereof robbeth God of his glory, and giveth it to ſtocks and ſtones, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by Gods word accurſed. And hee that will bring theſe ſpirituall Harlots, out of their lurking corners, into Publick Churches and Temples, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fornication may bee there openly, of all men and women without ſhame committed with them, no doubt that perſon is curſed of God, and twice curſed; And all good and godly men will ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> and their <hi>Amen</hi> will take effect alſo.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Homil.</hi> 3. <hi>againſt Idol. pa.</hi> 45. <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is moſt abominable before God, cannot poſſibly bee eſcaped and avoided, without the aboliſhing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Images and Pictures in Temples and Churches: For that Idolatry is to Images and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, ſpecially in Temples and Churches, an inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable accident (as they terme it;) ſo that Images
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156945:9"/>in Churches, and Idolatry goe both together, and therefore the one cannot be avoyded, except the other (ſpecially in all publike places) be deſtroyed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make Images, and publickly to ſet them up in Temples and Churches, places appointed peculiarly to the Service of God, is to make Images to the uſe of Religion; and not onely againſt this precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt make no manner of Image;</hi> But againſt this alſo; <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip them.</hi> Doth not our Church herein apparently confirme the judgement of <hi>Tertull. Colit qui facit,</hi> hee worſhippeth them, that maketh them.</p>
            <p>Yet againe, our Church in the <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>againſt Idol. pag.</hi> 62. <hi>out of</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine, Images placed in Churches are as it were in the appointed place, and heigth of honour and worſhip</hi> (as S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>where the living God only (and not dead ſtocks &amp; ſtones) is to be worſhipped.</hi> Which ſentence is more at large, recited by our learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> in his reply 514. in theſe words: <hi>They ſay we know that Images are creatures corruptible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee neither uſe them nor take them as Gods:</hi> And thus they think themſelves wiſe men, that can know that which birds and children be able to know: Even ſo the Heathen were wont to ſay of their Idols. But Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Very children know that theſe Images have eyes and ſee not, mouthes and ſpeak not:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then doth the holy Ghoſt ſo often teach and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us the ſame thing, in the Scripture as if we knew it not? He anſwereth, <hi>Quia ſpecies membrorum in emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenti collocata ſuggeſtu, cum honorari &amp; adorari caperit à multudine, parit in unoquoque ſordidiſsimum erroris af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum:</hi> Becauſe the Image of members ſet up in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent roome, when it is once honoured and adored by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156945:10"/>the multitude bringeth forth in every one of them, a moſt vile affection of their errour: And againe, <hi>Cùm in his ſedibus locantur, honorabili ſublimitate, ut a precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, &amp; immolantibus attendantur, ipſa ſimilitudine ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matorum membrorum atque ſenſuum, quamvis ſenſu &amp; animâ careant, afficiunt infirmos animos; ut vivere at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſpirare videantur:</hi> When they are placed in ſuch ſeats, in an honourable ſublimity, that they may bee ſeene by thoſe that offer up prayſe and prayer, by the very likeneſſe of living members and ſenſes, although they are voyd of life and ſenſe, infirme ſpirits are ſo affected, that they ſeeme really to live and breath: And againe, <hi>Quis adorat, vel orat intuens Simulacrum, qui non ſic afficitur, ut ab ea exaudiri ſeputet?</hi> Who worſhippeth or prayeth looking upon an Image, and is not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in conceit, that the Image heareth him? Marke, he doth not ſay, <hi>adorat Simulacrum,</hi> but, <hi>orat intuens Simu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrum,</hi> as of purpoſe to meet with theſe vaine and felſe excuſes and diſtinctions, which that old Serpent the Divell (ſaith, the Ancient Doctor of the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Clemens</hi>) uttereth by the mouthes of certain men. Doth it not ſtand every man in hand to take heed how hee liſten to the ſubtilties of that Serpent, who was a lyer and a murderer from the beginning, and taught our firſt Parents to diſtinguiſh, and exclude themſelves out of Paradiſe? And is not this ſufficient to ſhew, how both the godly Fathers of the Primitive Church, and the reverend Biſhops of our Reformed Church, have all agreed to that expoſition of <hi>Tertullian, Colit qui facit, vel qui locat?</hi> Hee worſhippeth them, who maketh them, or ſetteth them up.</p>
            <p>But why then is this word <hi>(to worſhip it)</hi> added in ſome places? To which three anſwers are made; the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156945:10"/>firſt, <hi>ex vi termini;</hi> for the particle [To] doth not only ſignifie the intention of the Agent, but many times the conſequent of the Act; as in that of our <hi>Saviour Chriſt, Matth.</hi> 5. He that looketh on a woman <hi>[to luſt, &amp;c.]</hi> The meaning is not only with an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to luſt, but to look ſo, as luſt doth follow: Whereupon our Saviour addeth; <hi>If thine eye cauſe thee to offend, pluck it out, &amp;c.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> putteth the caſe, that ſome may bee provoked to offend, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man eat a thing offered to an Idoll; and although he granteth that meat is a thing indifferent, yet hee addeth; <hi>If meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no meat, while the world ſtandeth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. So here the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent is to be avoyded.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>ex conſequentia ſuppoſiti:</hi> For where the ſecond Commandement is, <hi>Thou ſhalt make no Image, &amp;c.</hi> Hee that will adde this clauſe, to the intent to worſhip it, doth utterly evacuate and overthrow the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall part of the Commandement. For it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. and 13. and many other places of Scripture, that God ordained this Law to bee a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall Law, and the offenders to bee puniſhed by the Magiſtrate; which is not poſſible, if it be reſtrained to the intent; for <hi>de occultis cordium Indicabit Chriſtus,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; cogitationis poenam nemo patitur;</hi> ſayth the Law; As if a man ſhould ſtab an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and yet ſay he meant not to kill him, or as if one ſhould lie with another mans wife, and yet ſay he did it not to the intent to commit Adultery; will this excuſe him? Is it not an abſurd thing to conſter a Law according to the conceit of an offender, and not according to the ſentence of the Judge, or Judiciall Interpreters? So we have ſeene before, that the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156945:11"/>Divines both of the Primitive Church, and of our own preſent Church, doe agree in this, that <hi>colit qui facit, colit qui locat in honorabili ſublimitate;</hi> hee worſhippeth them who maketh them, he worſhippeth them who ſetteth them in an high place of honour; Never regarding the intent; and that to ſet up an Image aloft in the Church, with what intent ſoever, is not onely againſt this precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make any Image,</hi> but againſt this alſo, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe, nor worſhip it;</hi> The third <hi>ex ſenſu mandati;</hi> for it is anſwered alſo by our Learned Catechiſmes, that in the commandements, one ſinne is put commonly for all of the ſame ranke; yea for all inſtruments, occaſions, <hi>per Synechdochen ſpeciei.</hi> And this prohibition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Images, was (as <hi>Tertull.</hi> ſayth) <hi>ad eradicandam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriam Idololatriae,</hi> to ſubvert the cauſes of Idolatry: Alſo commonly the greateſt ſinne is named, to make all the reſt more odious. Therefore this word <hi>[to worſhip it]</hi> is not put to reſtraine, but to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate.</p>
            <p>Let us now therefore come to another point of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> expoſition, and ſee how that alſo is confirmed, both by the Ancient Fathers of the Primitive Church, and by the now reverend Fathers of our Church; <hi>Colit qui patitur: quaedam patientia eſt Idololatria,</hi> he worſhips them that permits them: ſome kinde of permiſſion is Idolatry, ſayth he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>againſt Idol. pa.</hi> 22. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> a very holy and learned man, who lived in <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperours time, vriteth thus to <hi>Iohn</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of Jeruſalem:
<q>I entred (ſayth <hi>Epiphanius</hi>) into a certaine Church to pray; I found there in it a linnen-cloth hanging in the Church doore painted, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156945:11"/>having in it the Image of Chriſt, (as it were) or of ſome other Saint, (for I remember not well whoſe Image it was;) Therefore when I did ſee the Image of a man hanging in the Church of Chriſt, contrary to the authority of the Scriptures, I did teare it, and gave counſell to the Keepers of the Church, that they ſhould winde a poore man that was dead in the ſayd cloth, and ſo bury him.</q> And afterwards, the ſayd <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſending another cloth unpainted, for that painted one which he had torne, to the ſaid Patriarch writeth thus.
<q>I pray you, will the Elders of that place, to receive this cloth which I have ſent by this bearer, and command them, that from henceforth no ſuch painted clothes, contrary to our Religion, be hanged up in the Church of Chriſt.</q> And this Epiſtle, as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be read of many, did Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> himſelfe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate into the Latin tongue, ſayth our Church in the Homily; adding further certain proofes that S. <hi>Hierom</hi> had this holy and learned Biſhop <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in moſt high eſtimation, and therefore did tranſlate this Epiſtle, as a writing of Authority: And thereupon obſerveth theſe ſpeciall points: Firſt, that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> judged it contrary to Chriſtian Religion, and to the Authority of the Scriptures to have any Images in Chriſts Church. Secondly, that he rejected not onely carved, graven, and moulten Images, but alſo painted Images out of Chriſts Church: Thirdly, that he regarded not whether it were the Image of Chriſt, or of any other Saint, but being an Image would not ſuffer it in the Church: Fourthly, that he did not only remove it out of the Church, but with a vehement zeale tare it in ſunder; and exhorted that a Corſe ſhould be wrapped and buried in it, judging it meet for nothing, but to rot in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156945:12"/>the Earth. Thus doth our Church and all our Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops, not only allow the judgement, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the fact, and zeale of <hi>Epiphanius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame points were obſerved upon this Epiſtle of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> by our godly and learned Biſhops, in the time of King <hi>Edward,</hi> in their reaſons exhibited to the ſaid King, to ſhew why they would not agree to ſuffer Images in Churches, as appeareth in the book of Martyrs, pag. 1929. a book allowed by all our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Church, and lately new Printed, and ſet forth this laſt yeere, and appointed by our Canons, to to be ſet up in all our Cathedrall Churches, for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to read, that Will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. againſt Idols <hi>pag.</hi> 61. Suffer Images to bee ſet up in the Churches and Temples; yee ſhall in vaine bid them beware of Images (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth) and flee Idolatry, as all the Scripture warne us: yee ſhall in vaine preach and teach them againſt Idolatry; for a number will notwithſtanding fall headlong into it; what by the nature of Images, what by the inclination of their owne corrupt nature. Wherefore as a man given to luſt, to ſit downe by a ſtrumpet, is to tempt God: ſo it is likewiſe to erect an Idoll in this prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans nature to Idolatry, nothing elſe but a tempting, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> opinion is, appeareth before. <hi>Quis adorat, vel orat intuens ſimulacrum, &amp;c.</hi> Who worſhippeth or prayeth looking upon an Image, and is not perſwaded in minde that the Image heareth him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. againſt Idols <hi>pag.</hi> 49. What meaneth it that Chriſtian men after the uſe of the Gentile Idolaters, cap and kneele before Images, <hi>&amp; infra:</hi> is not this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156945:12"/>ſtooping and kneeling before them, adoration of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chemnic. in exam. Deus uſum ſimulacrorum ad cultum, ſimpliciten numerat inter Deos alienos, &amp; ita prohibet at nullus eluſtoni aut acceptioni locus eſſe poſsit. Et infra, in ſtatuis enim, per ſtatuas, ſeu ad ſtatuas ſeu imagines, Deus nec ſe, nec Angelos, nec Sanctos, nec ullam creaturam vult coli.</hi> The uſe of Images for ſervice, is by God ſimply reckoned amongſt ſtrange Gods; and therefore he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth all manner of deluſions or exceptions. And further, for God will not have himſelfe, nor his Angels, nor Saints, nor any creature worſhipped, either in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, by ſtatues, or before ſtatues, or Images.</p>
            <p>And againe, he citeth another ſentence of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Eſtote memores, ne in Eccleſias Imagines inferatis, neque in Sanctorum Caemiteriis eas ſtatuatis; ſed perpetuò circumferte Deum in cordibus veſtris: Quin etiam ne in Domo communi tolerentur; Non enim fas eſt Chriſtianum per oculos ſuſpenſum teneri, ſed per occupatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mentis.</hi> Be you carefull that you bring no Images into Churches, nor into the Chappels of Gods people; but alwayes carry God in your hearts; for it is not lawfull that a Chriſtian ſhould be held in buſineſſes of the eye, but in contemplation of the minde. Mark what he ſaith, that it is not lawfull by Gods Law (which is ſignified by the word, <hi>Fas; fas jus divinum eſt</hi>) that a Chriſtian ſhould be held by the eyes, but by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his minde.</p>
            <p>But our common Catechiſmes allowed, and often printed, moſt plainly teach the ſame doctrine: namely the Catechiſme called Mr. <hi>Balls</hi> Catechiſme, the eighth Edition, 1631. <hi>page</hi> 176. upon the ſecond Commandement, to this Queſtion; <hi>What is here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden?</hi> He anſwereth, <hi>inter alia, making of Images for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156945:13"/>a religious uſe, Levit.</hi> 19.4. and 26.1. worſhipping God in, at, or before an Image, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip grounded only upon good intent or cuſtome, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. So the learned Catechiſme of Doctor <hi>Mayer,</hi> not only allowed, but commanded, in the fourth Edition, 1630. <hi>page</hi> 212. <hi>What are wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the ſecond Commandement? Anſw. All outward Idolatry, which is,</hi> 1. <hi>By making any Image of God, or of any creature to bee worſhipped.</hi> 2. <hi>By falling downe before any Image.</hi> 3. <hi>By ſerving God after our owne ſantaſies,</hi> and <hi>page</hi> 216. The ſecond kinde of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry is the falling downe before an Image, whether with an intention the better to be put in minde of God, or of any Saint, or by bowing before the Image, to give worſhip to the thing repreſented, or ignorantly only according to the tradition of the fathers. For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, or under what pretence ſoever, if the knee be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly bowed, before any Image, Idolatry is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and this Commandement broken: So the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Doctor <hi>Mayer,</hi> with the conſent of all our Church; to which muſt be added, that it is a point of Gods glory and worſhip, to be alone in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, before whom not only all the earth muſt be ſilent, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.20. but the moſt holy Angels, Cherubins and Seraphins muſt hide their faces, and cover themſelves: yea, both heaven and earth muſt flie away before him, <hi>Apo.</hi> 20.11. And therfore in his Temple, before him only we muſt performe thoſe duties which the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſo often calleth us to doe, namely, to come before him only, to bow before him, to kneele before him to worſhip before him, to ſpeak before him, to ſing before him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.96.98.100. &amp;c. even before him only in whoſe Temple all things muſt ſet forth his glory,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156945:13"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.9. and who hath moſt ſolemnely ſworne, that he will not give his glory to any other, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42. <hi>For the Lord ſhall riſe up, as in Mount Perazim, hee ſhall bee wrath, as in the valley of Gibeon, that he may doe his work, his ſtrange work, and performe his act, his ſtrange act, Eſa.</hi> 28. Let us therefore returne and apply this to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Scripture pronounced in our Common prayer book, and expounded in our Homilies:</p>
            <q>Curſed are the worſhippers of Images.</q>
            <p>And againe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>Curſed is he that maketh the blinde to goe out of the way.</hi> This curſe is read and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in our Churches yearly, <hi>Martii</hi> 6. and upon every Aſhwedneſday, by the Canon of our Common prayer book, and is thus applied by our Church in her Homily. <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>againſt Idols pag.</hi> 55. I will out of Gods word make this generall argument againſt all ſuch makers, maintainers, and ſetters up of Images in publick places. And firſt of all I will begin with the words of our Saviour Chriſt: <hi>Woe bee to that man by whom an offence is given. Woe be to him that offendeth one of theſe little ones, or weak ones. Better were it for him that a mil-ſtone were hanged about his neck, and he caſt into the middeſt of the ſea and drowned, than hee ſhould offend one of theſe little ones, or weak ones.</hi> And in <hi>Deut.</hi> God himſelfe denounceth him accurſed, <hi>that maketh the blinde to wander out of the way.</hi> And in <hi>Levit. Thou ſhalt not lay a ſtumbling block, or ſtone before the blinde.</hi> But Images in Churches and Temples have been, bee, and ever will bee offences and ſtumbling blocks, eſpecially to the weak, ſimple, and blinde common people, deceiving their hearts by the cunning of the Artificer (as the Scriptures expreſly in ſundry
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156945:14"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:156945:14"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156945:15"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:156945:15"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:156945:16"/>places doe teſtifie) and ſo bringing them to Idolatry; therefore woe bee to the erecter, ſetter up, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of Images in Churches and Temples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Article</hi> 22. <hi>Anal. Propoſ.</hi> 3. The Romiſh doctrine concerning Images is fond, and not warranted by the holy Scripture, nor conſonant, but contrary unto it.</p>
            <q>Proofes out of the word of God.</q>
            <p>Images are ſuch an abomination to the Lord, as to make them among all men odious: he deſcribeth the vanity of them by his Prophets, as that they are the doctrine of vanity, the work of errors, the teachers of lies, ſilver and gold, the work of mens hands, vanity, &amp;c. He giveth a ſtraight commandement not to bow down to them, nor worſhip them, not to make them, to flie from them; yea to deſtroy both Images themſelves, the Idolaters, and the enticers to Idolatry: Hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth greatly, and praiſeth ſuch men as have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Images, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He finally curſeth the Images themſelves, the Image-makers, and the Image-ſervers, or worſhippers.</p>
            <p>This Expoſition of the Article above ſaid is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by all our Church, and ſo publiſhed. And his Majeſty by his Declaration hath ratified theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, commanding all his Subjects to continue in the uniforme profeſſion of the ſame, prohibiting the leaſt difference from them, and declaring, that all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy men within his Realme agree in the uſuall literall meaning of the ſaid Articles. Which uſuall literall meaning can be no other, than that which is allowed by the authority of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and namely upon the 22 Article in the words above. Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his book of the old Religion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156945:16"/>
               <hi>cap.</hi> 10. commendeth the fact of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and his famous Epiſtle, which (ſaith he) is honoured by the tranſlation of S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> concerning the Image found by him in the Church of the village of <hi>Anablatha,</hi> though out of his owne Dioceſſe, how he tore it in an holy zeale, and wrote to the Biſhop of the place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him that no ſuch Pictures might bee made contrary to our Religion — <hi>&amp; infra.</hi> Some flie (ſaith he) to the diſtinction of Images and Idols, a diſtinction without a difference of their owne making, not of Gods. To be ſure God takes order for both: ye ſhall make you no Idol, nor graven Image, nor reare you up any ſtanding Image, neither ſhall yee ſet up any Image of ſtone in your land to bow downe to it. And againe, wee may well ſhut up all with that curſe in Mount <hi>Gerezim:</hi> Curſed be the man that maketh any graven or molten Image an abomination to the Lord, the work of the hands of Craftſman, and putteth it in a ſecret place: and all the people ſhall ſay, Amen; and ſurely their <hi>Durandus,</hi> after he hath cited divers Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures againſt Idols, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>Num.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at laſt concludes, <hi>ex his &amp; ſimilibus, &amp;c.</hi> By theſe and the like Authorities is condemned the too much uſe of Images. And againe, the holy jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of the Almighty will not abide any of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour divided with his creature: and what ever worſhip more than meere humane is imparted to the creature, ſets it in Rivality with our Maker. So the learned and eloquent Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his book of the old Religion. Now whether the ſetting up of Images in Churches be not <hi>nimius uſus Imaginum,</hi> upon all that which hath beene ſaid before; whether the ſetting up of them <hi>in honorabthi ſublimitate</hi> (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156945:17"/>appointed place and height of honour and worſhip, where the living God only is to be worſhipped (as the Homily out S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh) be not a worſhip more than meere humane; let every man judge. Truly S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in his book <hi>de fuga ſaeculi,</hi> agreeth with the Fathers above cited, ſaying, <hi>Eccleſia inanes Idaeas, &amp; varias neſcit ſimulacrorum figuras.</hi> Doctor <hi>Vſher</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Armah,</hi> in his anſwer to the <hi>Ieſuits Challenge,</hi> likewiſe utterly condemneth the ſetting up of ſuch Images and Pictures in Churches, citing and approving the ſentences and judgements of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe, Amphilochius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Iconium, Serenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Maſsilia,</hi> and many others, which book now lately was new Printed, <hi>in Anno</hi> 1631. Did all theſe goe upon Temporall reaſons? Doth our Common prayer book pronounce, and yearly renew ſuch heavie and dreadfull Curſes, for a Temporall reſpect only, as our late Imagers, or Imaginers would have us to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine? Why do then our common Catechiſmes give us this generall doctrine, and inſtruction, that where one vice or ſinne is forbidden, all of the ſame kinde, and that neceſſarily, depend thereon; as alſo the leſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or enticement thereunto are likewiſe forbidden; upon the words of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.21.22. &amp;c. and 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.15. To this let us adde the heavie ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, judgements, and curſes pronounced by God againſt thoſe that ſuffer, and doe not oppoſe themſelves againſt the open enimies and contemners of God and his lawes. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Curſe yee Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe yee bitterly the Inhabitants thereof; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> So <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8. ſheweth how ſeverely <hi>Gideon</hi> puniſhed the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:156945:17"/>for refuſing to help him in his purſuit of Gods enimies: ſo <hi>Iudg.</hi> 21. is ſet forth the fearfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo terribly executed upon the men of <hi>Iabes;</hi> becauſe they came not to help the Iſraelites, and to aſſiſt them in the puniſhment of that great ſinne committed, and maintained by the Benjamites: Wherein alſo is to bee noted, that that holy man <hi>Phinehaz</hi> was at that time alive, and was high Prieſt, without whoſe adviſe they did nothing. So <hi>Ier.</hi> 48. <hi>Curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord negligently or deceitfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. <hi>Hee that is an hireling</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) <hi>and not the Shepherd, and whoſe owne the ſheep are not, ſeeth the Wolfe comming, and leaveth the ſheep, and fleeth, and the Wolf catcheth and ſcattereth the ſheep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zach.</hi> 11. <hi>Woe to the idle Shepherd that leaveth the flock, the ſword ſhall bee upon his arme, and upon his right eye; his arme ſhall be cleane dried up, and his right eye ſhall be darkened.</hi> I know a ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding may be of the arme, and the right eye. But are not the judgements of God many times corporally executed? And many a man (without offence) ask how the Paſtors of ſome Churches, wherein Images are ſet up, doe by their eyes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Iezebel,</hi> &amp;c. So the common Rules and Maxims of all Lawes.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſentientes &amp; agentes pari paenâ conſtringantur.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bis peccat qui peccanti obſequium accommodat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui non vetat peccarecum poſsit, jubet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let the conſenter and the actor receive equality of puniſhment.</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:156945:18"/>
                  <l>He is a double offender who abetteth an offence.</l>
                  <l>He who ſorbiddeth not an offence when it lies in his power, commandeth it.</l>
               </lg> 
            </q>
            <p>And of the ſeverall kindes of conſents, <hi>Lyra in Praeceptorio.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſulo, praecipio, conſentio, provoco, laudo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non relego culpam, non punio, non reprehendo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Participo, defendo, reum me talia reddunt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I counſell, bid, conſent, provoke, commend,</l>
                  <l>I ſuffer, puniſh not, nor reprehend,</l>
                  <l>I ſhare in, I defend a crime; theſe bring</l>
                  <l>Me into judgement for the ſelfe ſame thing.</l>
               </lg> 
            </q>
            <p>So <hi>Anſtaſ. Damaſus,</hi> and <hi>Innocentius in Decret. Error cui non reſiſtitur, approbatur; &amp; veritas cùm non defenditur, opprimitur: Negligere quippe cum poſsis, perturbare perverſos, nihil eſt aliud quàm fovere. Neque caret ſcrupulo ſocietatis occultae, qui facinori manifeſto definit obviare.</hi> An errour which is not reſiſted, is approved; and truth when it is not defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is oppreſſed: For to neglect the oppoſition of the perverſe when it lies in thy power, is no other than to maintaine them: Nor is he free from the cenſure of private conſent, who withſtandeth not a manifeſt offence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aug.</hi> and out of him the Decree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vterque reus eſt, &amp; qui veritatem occultat, &amp; qui mendacium dicit; quia &amp; ille prodeſſe non vult, &amp; iſte nocere deſiderat.</hi> Both are guilty, as well he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealeth the truth, as he that telleth a ly; becauſe the one will not doe good, the other deſires to doe harme.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:156945:18"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> and the Decree.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non ſolum ille proditor eſt veritatis, qui transgredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens veritatem, palum promendacio Loquitur, ſed etiam ille qui veritatem non liberè pronunciat, quum liberè pronunciare oporet, aut non liberè veritatem defendit, quum liberè defendere convenit.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>He is not only a traitour to trueth, who tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the trueth telleth a lie; but hee alſo, who freely ſpeaketh not the trueth when it is needfull, or doth not freely defend the trueth when it is expedient ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> again, and out of him the Decree.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecce (inquiunt ut dicit Propheta) Recedite &amp; exite indo, &amp; immundum ne tetegeritis; Quid eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum tangere, niſi peccatis conſentire? Quid eſt exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re inde, niſi facere quod pertinet ad correctionem? quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pro unius cujuſque gradu atque perſona (ſalvâ pace) fieri poteſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Behold (ſay they as ſayes the Prophet) <hi>depart and come out from thence, touch not the unclean thing.</hi> What is meant by touching the unclean thing but conſenting to ſinne? what by comming out from thence, but doing what appertaines to its reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? as much as without breach of peace may bee done, according to every mans degree and perſon.</p>
            <p>Hereupon our Church in <hi>Hom.</hi> 3. againſt. <hi>Idol. p.</hi> 75. thus concludeth. Ye have heard it evidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in theſe Homilies againſt Idolatry, by Gods word, the Doctors of the Church, Eccleſiaſticall, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoryes Reaſon &amp; experience, that Images have bin &amp; be worſhipped, and ſo Idolatry committed to them by infinite multitudes, to the greater offence of Gods Majeſty, and infinite danger of ſoules; and that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156945:19"/>cannot poſsibly be ſeparated from Images ſet up in Churches and Temples, gilded and decked gloriouſly, and that therefore our Images be indeed very Idols; and ſo all the prohibitions, Lawes, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, threatnings of horrible plagues, aſwell Temporall as Eternall contained in the Scriptures, concerning Idols, and the makers, mainteyners and worſhippers of them, appertaine alſo to our Images ſet up in Churches, and Temples, and to the makers, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyners, and worſhippers of them. And all thoſe names of Abomination which Gods word giveth to the Idols of the Gentiles, appertaine alſo to our Images ſet up in Churches and Temples, being Idols like to them, and having like Idolatry committed to them. And Gods owne mouth in the Holy Scripture calleth them vanities, lies, Deceits, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, filthineſſe, dung, miſchiefe, and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the Lord. Wherefore Gods moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wrath and our moſt dreadfull danger cannot be avoyded without the deſtruction and aboliſhing of all ſuch Images and Idols out of the Church and Temple of God. Which to accompliſh, God put into the mindes of all Chriſtian Princes. And in the meane time let us take heede and be wiſe, O yee beloved of the Lord, and let us have no ſtrange Gods, &amp;c. So the Homily of our Church.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Iewels</hi> Reply. <hi>pa.</hi> 517. The beſt remedy in this behalfe, and moſt agreeable with Gods word, is utterly to aboliſh the cauſe of the ill.</p>
            <p>So the godly King <hi>Ezekias</hi> took downe and brake in peeces the brazen Serpent, notwithſtanding Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelfe by Gods ſpeciall commandement had erected it, notwithſtanding it were an expreſſe figure
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156945:19"/>of Chriſt hanging upon the Croſſe: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it had continued ſo many yeares, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God by it had wrought ſo many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</p>
            <p>So the godly Biſhop <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rent in ſunder an Image painted in a cloth, and ſaid, it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Commandement, a thing ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and unmeet for the Church and people of God, notwithſtanding it were the Image of Chriſt. So the godly Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> made his Proclamation over all his Dominions in this ſort: <hi>Signum Servatoris noſtri quocunque loco repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, tolli jubemus:</hi> We ſtraightly command, that the Image of our Saviour be taken downe, in what place ſoever it ſhall bee found; notwithſtanding it were the Image of our Saviour. So it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in the late Councell of <hi>Mogunce,</hi> that when Images happen to bee abuſed by the people, they bee either notably altered, or utterly aboliſhed. Neither doth God through all his holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures any where condemne Image-breakers, but expreſly and every where hee condemneth Image-worſhippers, and Image-makers: yea he ſaith, <hi>they are ſnares to catch the ignorant:</hi> Hee knoweth the inclination of the heart of man; and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Accurſed be he, that leadeth the blinde out of the way;</hi> and <hi>accurſed be he, that layeth a ſtumbling block to overthrow the blinde.</hi> So concludeth the reverend and learned Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> and all our Church with him.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:156945:20"/>
            <p>So all the holy Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs Doctors, and Saints of God now triumphant in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who ſhall ſit upon Thrones as Aſſeſſors with our Saviour Chriſt, and judge the world, (as the Scriptures ſpeak) in their books and monuments which they have left behinde them to teſtifie their mindes, doe unanimouſly pronounce the like ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences unto us. And if wee could heare them ſpeaking in heaven, wee ſhould heare their voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as loud as Thunders, or Trumpets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, that wee muſt not imagine that they will ſpeak otherwiſe in heaven, than they did upon earth.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore conclude with that holy Doctor S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and that moſt bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the name of all the reſt. <hi>Ergo fratres mei, quot quot habetis inter vos, qui adhuc amore ſaeculi praegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantur, avaros, perjuros, adulteros, inſpectores nuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;c. quicquid inter vos malorum eſſe noſtis, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum poteſtis improbate, ut corde recedatis; &amp; redar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guite, ut exeatis inde; &amp; nolite conſentire, ut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum ne tangatis.</hi> Therefore my brethren, as many as you have amongſt you, who are overcharged with the love of this world, coverous perſons, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers, adulterers, beholders of vanity, &amp;c. whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever evills you know amongſt you, reject them as much as you can; depart from them in your hearts; reprove them, that you may come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; and conſent not unto them, that you may not touch the uncleane thing. <hi>Come
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156945:20"/>out from among them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and touch not the uncleane thing; I will receive you, and yee ſhall bee my ſonnes, and my daughters,</hi> ſaith the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <trailer>Chriſto Gloria.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
